Cornelia Bryce Pinchot Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Cornelia Bryce Pinchot Papers 1899-1960 1918-1947
MSS36269
Pinchot, Cornelia Bryce, 1881-1960
248,000 items
573 containers plus 1 oversize
229.6 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Politician, political activist, and wife of Gifford Pinchot of Pennsylvania. Correspondence, political campaign papers and speeches, gardening file, and financial records relating to Pinchot's political activities and the Pinchot family.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Pinchot, Cornelia Bryce, 1881-1960.; Pinchot, Gifford, 1865-1946.
Organizations
League of Women Voters of Pennsylvania.; National Women's Trade Union League of America.; United States. Congress--Elections, 1928.; United States. Congress--Elections, 1932.
Subjects
Children--Legal status, laws, etc.--United States.; Gardening--United States.; Labor movement--United States.; Women labor union members--United States.; Women political candidates--Pennsylvania.; Women--Employment--Law and legislation--United States.; Women--Suffrage--United States.
Places
Pennsylvania--Politics and government--1865-1950.
Occupations
Governors' spouses.; Political activists.; Politicians.; Suffragists.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Cornelia Bryce Pinchot, politician, political activist, and wife of Gifford Pinchot of Pennsylvania, were given to the Library of Congress by Cornelia and Gifford Pinchot and the Pinchot family in several installments between 1941 and 1990. Additional material has been received through gift and transfer, 1955-1989.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Cornelia Bryce Pinchot are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1881, Aug. 26 Born, Newport, R.I.
1914 Married Gifford Pinchot (died 1946)
1915 Birth of only child, Gifford Bryce Pinchot
1923 1927 First Lady of Pennsylvania
1923 Advocated enforcement of Volstead Act prohibiting sale of liquor
1928 Ran unsuccessfully for Congress
1931 1935 First Lady of Pennsylvania
1932 Ran unsuccessfully for Congress
1934 Walked the picket line in support of striking laundry and garment workers, New York, N.Y. Sought governorship of Pennsylvania as an independent; later withdrew
1949 Delegate, United Nations Conference on the Conservation and Utilization of Resources, Lake Success, N. Y.
1960, Sept. 9 Died, Washington, D.C.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Cornelia Bryce Pinchot (1881-1960) span the years 1899-1960 with the bulk of the material dating from 1918 to 1947. The papers reflect Pinchot's activities in the suffrage movement, union organizing for women workers, lobbying for legislative protection for working women and children, involvement in the League of Women Voters and the Women's Trade Union League, as wife of the governor of Pennsylvania, and her two campaigns for a Congressional seat. Her papers also contain personal papers, including financial records, correspondence with her husband Gifford Pinchot, medical records such as material documenting her treatments for repeated miscarriages, and papers regarding the Pinchot's home and gardens at "Grey Towers" in Milford, Pennsylvania.
The Pinchot Papers are organized in three parts. Part I, 1918-1947, by far the largest, came to the library with the Gifford Pinchot Papers and was later organized as a separate collection. Part II, 1927-1960, consisting mostly of post-1940s material, was boxed and described largely as received. Part III, 1909-1941, represents the smallest portion of the collection and contains personal and organization material organized alphabetically by topic or type of material.
Organization of the Papers
The collection is arranged in three parts:
Part I: 1918-1947
Part II: 1927-1960
Part III: 1909-1941
Container List
- Part I: 1918-1947 (Box I:1-492)
  - Correspondence, 1918-1947 (Box I:1-420)
    General and topical correspondence.
    Arranged chronologically, mostly by year, and therein by topic or type of material.
    - 1918 (Box I:1)
      - Personal letters
      - Personal correspondence (Box I:2)
        - A-L
        - M-Z (Box I:3)
      - Food (Box I:4)
      - Suffrage, etc., 1916-1918 (Box I:5)
    - 1919 (Box I:6)
      - General Letters
        - A-F
        - G-R (Box I:7)
        - S-Z (Box I:8)
      - National Women's Trade Union League (Box I:9)
      - Suffrage
      - Suffrage (Box I:10)
    - 1920
      - General Correspondence
        - A-D
        - Q-Z (Box I:11)
      - Personal Correspondence (Box I:12)
        - A-L
        - M-Z (Box I:13)
    - 1921 (Box I:14)
      - A-E
      - F-L (Box I:15)
      - M-R (Box I:16)
      - R-Z (Box I:17)
    - 1921-1922, Bryn Mawr Correspondence (Box I:18)
    - 1922 (Box I:19)
      - Women's Trade Union League, A-Z
      - Personal Correspondence (Box I:20)
        - A-B
        - C-E (Box I:21)
        - F-H (Box I:22)
        - Hu-L (Box I:23)
        - M-P (Box I:24)
        - Ph-St (Box I:25)
        - Su-Z (Box I:26)
        - Miscellaneous (Box I:27-28)
    - 1923 (Box I:29)
      - A-B
      - B-D (Box I:30)
      - E-G (Box I:31)
      - H-L (Box I:32)
      - L (Box I:33)
      - M-N (Box I:34)
      - O-R (Box I:35)
      - S (Box I:36)
      - T-Z (Box I:37)
    - 1923-1924 (Box I:38)
      - A-B
      - B (Box I:39)
      - B-C (Box I:40)
      - C (Box I:41)
      - D-E (Box I:42)
      - E-G (Box I:43)
      - G-H (Box I:44)
      - H-K (Box I:45)
      - L-M (Box I:46)
      - M-N (Box I:47)
      - O-P (Box I:48)
      - P (Box I:49)
      - P-S (Box I:50)
      - S (Box I:51)
      - T-W (Box I:52)
      - W (Box I:53)
      - R-Z (Box I:54)
      - Miscellaneous Correspondence, schools, 1923-1926 (Box I:55)
    - 1924 (Box I:56)
      - Miscellaneous Correspondence
        - Engagements Declined
        - American Peace Award, 1923-1926 (Box I:57)
        - National Women's Trade Union League, 1924
        - Information Service, 1923-1926 (Box I:58)
        - National Women's Trade Union League, 1926
    - 1924-1925 (Box I:59)
      - A-B
      - B-C (Box I:60)
      - C-D (Box I:61)
      - E-G (Box I:62)
      - H-K (Box I:63)
      - K-M (Box I:64)
      - M-P (Box I:65)
      - P (Box I:66)
      - Q-R (Box I:67)
      - R-S (Box I:68A)
      - R-T (Box I:68B)
      - U-Y (Box I:69)
    - 1925, suffrage (Box I:70)
    - 1925-1926 (Box I:71)
      - A-B
      - B-C (Box I:72)
      - C-D (Box I:73)
      - D-E (Box I:74)
      - F-G (Box I:75)
      - G-H (Box I:76)
      - H-L (Box I:77)
      - L-M (Box I:78)
      - M-N (Box I:79)
      - N-P (Box I:80)
      - P-R (Box I:81)
      - R-S (Box I:82)
      - S (Box I:83)
      - T-W (Box I:84)
      - W-Z (Box I:85)
    - 1926 (Box I:86)
      - Correspondence
        - A-Z
      - Senate Campaign (Box I:87)
        - A-Be
        - Be-By (Box I:88)
        - C-Cr (Box I:89)
        - D-Do (Box I:90)
        - Dr-Fo (Box I:91)
        - Fo-Gr (Box I:92)
        - A-D (Box I:93)
        - D-K (Box I:94)
        - K-S (Box I:95)
        - S-Z (Box I:96)
    - 1926-1927 (Box I:97)
      - A
      - B (Box I:98)
      - B-C (Box I:99)
      - C-F (Box I:100)
      - F-G (Box I:101)
      - G-I (Box I:102)
      - J-L (Box I:103)
      - M-O (Box I:104)
      - P (Box I:105)
      - R-S (Box I:106)
      - S (Box I:107)
      - S-W (Box I:108)
      - W-Y (Box I:109)
      - A-Z (Box I:110)
      - Miscellaneous (Box I:111)
    - 1927-1928 (Box I:112)
      - A-B
      - B-C (Box I:113)
      - C (Box I:114)
      - C-D (Box I:115)
      - E-G (Box I:116)
      - G-H (Box I:117)
      - H-L (Box I:118)
      - L-M (Box I:119)
      - M-N (Box I:120)
      - N-P (Box I:121)
      - P-R (Box I:122)
      - R (Box I:123)
      - S (Box I:124)
      - S-T (Box I:125)
      - T-V (Box I:126)
      - W-Z (Box I:127)
      - Senate Campaign (Box I:128-130)
        - Clippings
        - County Lists
        - Tatro Reports (Box I:131)
        - Campaign Correspondence (Box I:132)
          - A-B
          - C-D (Box I:133)
          - E-F (Box I:134)
          - F-H (Box I:135)
          - I-L (Box I:136)
          - L-N (Box I:137)
          - N-P (Box I:138)
          - R-S (Box I:139)
          - S-W (Box I:140)
          - W-Z (Box I:141)
    - 1929-1930 (Box I:142)
      - A-B
      - B (Box I:143)
      - B-C (Box I:144)
      - C-D (Box I:145)
      - D-F (Box I:146)
      - G (Box I:147)
      - G-H (Box I:148)
      - H-J (Box I:149)
      - K-L (Box I:150)
      - M-N (Box I:151)
      - N-P (Box I:152)
      - P (Box I:153)
      - P-S (Box I:154)
      - S (Box I:155)
      - S-T (Box I:156)
      - T-W (Box I:157)
      - W-Z (Box I:158)
    - 1930-1931 (Box I:159-160)
      - A
      - A-B (Box I:161)
      - B (Box I:162-163)
      - C (Box I:164)
      - C-D (Box I:165)
      - D-F (Box I:166)
      - F-G (Box I:167)
      - G (Box I:168)
      - G-H (Box I:169)
      - H (Box I:170)
      - H-K (Box I:171)
      - K (Box I:172)
      - L (Box I:173)
      - L-M (Box I:174)
      - M (Box I:175)
      - M-N (Box I:176)
      - O-P (Box I:177)
      - P (Box I:178)
      - P-R (Box I:179)
      - R-S (Box I:180)
      - S (Box I:181-182)
      - A-L (Box I:183)
      - L-W (Box I:184)
    - 1931 (Box I:185)
      - S-T
      - T-U (Box I:186)
      - U-W (Box I:187)
      - W-Z (Box I:188)
    - 1932 (Box I:189)
      - A-B
      - B (Box I:190-192)
      - B-C (Box I:193)
      - C (Box I:194)
      - C-D (Box I:195)
      - D-E (Box I:196)
      - E-F (Box I:197)
      - F-G (Box I:198)
      - G (Box I:199)
      - H (Box I:200-201)
      - H-J (Box I:202)
      - J-K (Box I:203)
      - K-L (Box I:204)
      - L-M (Box I:205)
      - M (Box I:206)
      - M-N (Box I:207)
      - O-P (Box I:208)
      - P (Box I:209-210)
      - P-R (Box I:211)
      - R (Box I:212-213)
      - R-S (Box I:214)
      - S (Box I:215-216)
      - S-T (Box I:217)
      - T-U (Box I:218)
      - V-W (Box I:219)
      - W (Box I:220)
      - W-Z (Box I:221)
      - Campaign Correspondence (Box I:222)
        - A-B
        - B-C (Box I:223)
        - C-E (Box I:224)
        - E-F (Box I:225)
        - G-H (Box I:226)
        - H-K (Box I:227)
        - K-M (Box I:228)
        - M (Box I:229)
        - M-P (Box I:230)
        - P-S (Box I:231)
        - S (Box I:232-234)
        - S-W (Box I:235)
        - V (Box I:236-237)
        - V-Z (Box I:238)
    - 1933 (Box I:239)
      - A
      - B (Box I:240-243)
      - C (Box I:244)
      - C-D (Box I:245)
      - D (Box I:246)
      - E-F (Box I:247)
      - F-G (Box I:248)
      - G (Box I:249-251)
      - H (Box I:252-254)
      - H-J (Box I:255)
      - K (Box I:256)
      - K-L (Box I:257)
      - L-M (Box I:258)
      - M (Box I:259-262)
      - M-N (Box I:263)
      - N-P (Box I:264)
      - P (Box I:265-266)
      - R (Box I:267-268)
      - R-S (Box I:269)
      - S (Box I:270-274)
      - S-T (Box I:275)
      - T-V (Box I:276)
      - W (Box I:277-278)
      - W-Z (Box I:279)
      - 1934 (Box I:280)
      - A
      - A-B (Box I:281)
      - B (Box I:282-284)
      - B-C (Box I:285)
      - C (Box I:286-287)
      - C-D (Box I:288)
      - D-E (Box I:289)
      - E-F (Box I:290)
      - F-G (Box I:291)
      - G (Box I:292-293)
      - G-K (Box I:294)
      - K-L (Box I:295)
      - L-M (Box I:296)
      - M (Box I:297-298)
      - M-N (Box I:299)
      - N-O (Box I:300)
      - O-P (Box I:301)
      - P (Box I:302)
      - P-R (Box I:303)
      - R (Box I:304)
      - R-S (Box I:305)
      - S (Box I:306-307)
      - S-U (Box I:308)
      - V-W (Box I:309)
      - W (Box I:310)
      - W-Z (Box I:311)
    - 1934-1935 (Box I:312-314)
      - H
      - I-J (Box I:315)
      - J (Box I:316)
    - 1935 (Box I:317)
      - A
      - B-Bu (Box I:318)
      - B-Ch (Box I:319)
      - Col-Cz (Box I:320)
      - D-E (Box I:321)
      - F (Box I:322)
      - G-Hi (Box I:323)
      - Ho-J (Box I:324)
      - K-Le (Box I:325)
      - Li-M (Box I:326)
      - Me-Ne (Box I:327)
      - O-P (Box I:328)
      - Q-Ri (Box I:329)
      - Ri-Sh (Box I:330)
      - Sn-St (Box I:331)
      - T-V (Box I:332)
      - W-Z (Box I:333)
    - 1936 (Box I:334)
      - Personal Correspondence
        - A-Bix
        - Bl-Col (Box I:335)
        - Con-Din (Box I:336)
        - Din-Fo (Box I:337)
        - G (Box I:338)
        - H (Box I:339)
        - I-L (Box I:340)
        - Li-O (Box I:341)
        - P-Q (Box I:342)
        - R (Box I:343)
        - S-T (Box I:344)
        - U-Z (Box I:345)
      - Campaign Correspondence (Box I:346)
        - A-E
        - F-G (Box I:347)
        - G-L (Box I:348)
        - L (Box I:349)
        - L-R (Box I:350)
        - S-W (Box I:351)
        - W (Box I:352)
        - W-Z (Box I:353)
    - 1937 (Box I:354)
      - A-Bir
      - Bir-Bot (Box I:355)
      - Bro-Col (Box I:356)
      - Col (Box I:357)
      - Col-Cows (Box I:358)
      - D-F (Box I:359)
      - G-Hi (Box I:360)
      - Ho-J (Box I:361)
      - K-Ma (Box I:362)
      - M (Box I:363)
      - N-Pi (Box I:364)
      - Pi-Ri (Box I:365)
      - S-T (Box I:366)
      - U-Z (Box I:367)
    - 1938 (Box I:368)
      - A-Bir
      - Bir-Col (Box I:369)
      - Con-Din (Box I:370)
      - Din-H (Box I:371)
      - Hi-Ki (Box I:372)
      - L-N (Box I:373)
      - O-Ra (Box I:374)
      - R-S (Box I:375)
      - T-Z (Box I:376)
    - 1939 (Box I:377)
      - A-Bro
      - Bry-Col (Box I:378)
      - D-G (Box I:379)
      - H-I (Box I:380)
      - K-L (Box I:381)
      - M-O (Box I:382)
      - P-Ri (Box I:383)
      - Ro-Z (Box I:384)
    - 1940 (Box I:385)
      - A-Bi
      - Bo-D (Box I:386)
      - E-Hi (Box I:387)
      - Ho (Box I:388)
      - I-O (Box I:389)
      - Pe-R (Box I:390)
      - S-Z (Box I:391)
    - 1941 (Box I:392)
      - A-Ca
      - Ca-D (Box I:393)
      - E-H (Box I:394)
      - I-L (Box I:395)
      - L-P (Box I:396)
      - P-R (Box I:397)
      - S-Wa (Box I:398)
      - Wa-Z (Box I:399)
    - 1942 (Box I:400)
      - A-L
      - L-Z (Box I:401)
    - 1942-1943 (Box I:402)
      - A-F
      - F-J (Box I:403)
      - L-U (Box I:404)
      - U-Z (Box I:405)
    - 1944 (Box I:406)
      - A-F
      - G-K (Box I:407)
      - L-Z (Box I:408)
    - 1945 (Box I:409)
      - A-F
      - F-S (Box I:410)
      - T-Z (Box I:411)
    - Mainly 1946 (includes some 1945 and 1947) (Box I:412)
      - Alphabetical File
        - A-G Ac 9375
        - H-R (Box I:413)
        - S-Z (Box I:414)
    - Mainly 1947 (Box I:415)
      - Alphabetical File
        - A
        - B-I (Box I:416)
        - J-P (Box I:417)
        - Q-Z (Box I:418)
    - 1922-1941 (Box I:419)
      - Miscellaneous Correspondence
    - Undated (Box I:420)
      - Guests Lists/Invitations
  - Subject File, undated (Box I:421-447)
    Mainly financial papers, garden files, and files from the U.S. Office of Civilian Defense and the Committee for National Morale.
    - Miscellaneous (Box I:421)
    - Financial Papers (Box I:422-425)
    - Garden Files (Box I:426)
      - A
      - B (Box I:427)
      - C-Cl (Box I:428)
      - Co-D (Box I:429)
      - E-Ga (Box I:430)
      - Ga-Gz (Box I:431)
      - H-J (Box I:432)
      - K-Le (Box I:433)
      - Li-M (Box I:434)
      - N-O (Box I:435)
      - P-Sa (Box I:436)
      - S (Box I:437)
      - St-Lim (Box I:438)
      - Lin-Z (Box I:439)
    - U.S. Office of Civilian Defense (Box I:440-445)
    - Committee for National Morale (Box I:446-447)
  - Speech File, 1920-1944 (Box I:448-472)
    Speeches, speech material, and press releases.
    - Speeches (Box I:448-461)
      - 1920-1929
      - 1931 (Box I:462)
      - 1932-1934 (Box I:463)
      - 1934 (Box I:464)
      - 1934-1935 (Box I:465)
      - 1935-1937 (Box I:466)
      - 1937 (Box I:467-468)
      - 1937-1938 (Box I:469-470)
      - 1938 (Box I:471)
      - 1939-1944 (Box I:472)
    - Speeches and press releases, 1930-1932 (Box I:473)
    - Miscellaneous (Box I:474)
    - Speech material (Box I:475-485)
  - Miscellany, undated (Box I:486-492)
    - Miscellaneous (Box I:486-490)
    - Material/Dress Samples/Recipes/Prescriptions (Box I:491)
    - Campaign Material (Box I:492)
- Part II: 1927-1960 (Box II:1-75)
  Correspondence, printed matter, photographs, journals, notes, address lists, financial material, reports, book drafts, radio scripts, and architectural and landscape plans.
  Organized largely as received.
  - General correspondence, L-S, 1941-1951 (Box II:1-5)
  - Clippings
  - Brochures
  - Pamphlets
  - General correspondence re Greece, 1947-1948 (Box II:6-11)
  - Pamphlets
  - Photographs
  - Journals and notes
  - General correspondence, 1947-1948 (Box II:12-15)
  - Clippings
  - Business correspondence, 1947
  - Pamphlets
  - United Nations, booklets, pamphlets, and reports, 1949 (Box II:16-17)
  - Address lists, 1941-1948 (Box II:18)
  - Business correspondence
  - General correspondence, 1948 (Box II:19-20)
  - Clippings
  - Reports
  - Business correspondence, 1946-1959 (Box II:21-24)
  - General correspondence (Box I:25-29)
    - A-F, 1952-1960
    - G-P, 1946-1959 (Box II:30-34)
  - General and business correspondence, 1950-1960 (Box II:35-42)
  - Account books, 1943-1959 (Box II:43-45, OV 46)
  - Address books
  - Letters by Cornelia Pinchot from Greece, 1947-1948
  - Conservation congress reports
  - Notebooks, undated
  - Book on North Carolina trees, incomplete
  - Passports
  - Conservation material
  - Blueprints and pictures (Box II:47-49)
  - Date books, 1952-1959
  - Natural History, 1939-1942
  - Voices, 1932-1942
  - Correspondence, undated
  - Manuscript of book, 1952
  - Miscellaneous files, 1949
  - Picture book and watercolor caricature
  - Business correspondence, 1939-1959 (Box II:50-52)
  - Business correspondence and correspondence of Gifford Pinchot, 1927-1949 (Box II:53-55)
  - Greek correspondence, 1947 (Box II:56-57)
  - Foreign Conservation Society
  - Family correspondence, 1947-1960 (Box II:58-61)
  - Financial papers, 1943-1960
  - Correspondence (Box II:62-65)
  - Clippings
  - Radio scripts, 1955
  - Pamphlets, 1949-1959
  - Correspondence (Box II:66-70)
  - Business correspondence, 1939-1951 (Box II:71-74)
  - Plans of “Grey Towers,” Milford, Pa. (Box II:75)
- Part III: 1909-1941 (Box III: 1-6)
  Correspondence, financial material, address lists, diary of a 1929 trip, medical records, and reports.
  Arranged alphabetically by topic or type of material.
  - Address lists, 1920, undated (Box III: 1)
  - Bryce family wills, 1912-1920
  - Consumers' League, 1919-1920, undated
  - Correspondence
    - Miscellaneous, 1914-1923, 1934, 1941, undated, (2 folders)
    - Pinchot, Amos, 1929
    - Pinchot, Gifford
      - 1914-1917, (2 folders)
      - 1918-1927, 1936-1938, undated, (6 folders) (Box III: 2)
  - Diary, 1929, (4 folders)
  - Financial material
    - 1915-1918
    - 1919-1928, (2 folders) (Box III: 3)
  - International suffrage conference, Rome, Italy, 1923
  - Labor issues, 1919-1922, undated
  - League of Women Voters
    - Correspondence
      - 1919, Feb.-1921, July, (7 folders)
      - 1921, Aug.-1923, Feb., undated, (4 folders) (Box III: 4)
    - Financial material, 1919-1922, undated, (2 folders)
    - Miscellany, 1919-1923, undated, (2 folders)
  - McCarthy, Charles, 1921
  - Medical records, 1919-1921, undated
  - Miscellany, 1921-1922, 1932, undated
  - National Women's Trade Union League (Box III: 5)
    - Correspondence, 1912-1922, undated, (8 folders)
    - Financial material, 1920-1922, undated, (2 folders)
    - Fire safety, 1911, undated
    - Miscellany, 1918-1923, undated
    - Names and addresses, 1918-1921, undated
    - Reports, 1920, undated (Box III: 6)
  - Pennsylvania Woman Suffrage Association, 1919, undated
  - Peter Cooper Glue Factory, New York, N.Y., 1909-1910
  - Prohibition
    - Correspondence, 1923, undated, (2 folders)
    - Law enforcement, 1923
  - Summer school for women workers in industry, Bryn Mawr College, Bryn Mawr, Pa.
    - Correspondence, 1922-1923, undated
    - Miscellany, 1921-1923, undated